hey guys welcome to concept and coding
and this is Shan and today we are going
to do the first topic of spring boot
that is Introduction to Spring Boot and
I will cover this thing what problem it
solves and its features and
advantages so let's start without
wasting any time so why spring boot
exists today what problem it solves
right how it is differ from Spring
framework there are lot of questions
about it so to total clarify about it
like the complete picture we have to go
little bit back when seets were popular
so back in
2015 and 2016 I worked a lot on sulet
and I know how hard it was to manage the
application and currently we are working
on a spring Boot and we know that how
easy it is compared to sulet so I will
not tell you about in depth depth about
sulet but at least I will tell you what
problem was exist in the sulet what
problem it solves okay so let's go so
that's why I mentioned before we talk
about a spring or spring boot first we
need to understand about sulet and sulet
container so these are the foundation
for building web application back in
2013 14 15 this suets are very popular
and these are you can say that the
foundation for the
web application spring and spring spring
boot internally uses the same concept
right so they sulet actually build the
foundation so what is sulet sulet is a
Java class which handles client request
processes it and Returns the response so
considered it as a class where you have
Define any one your
API input request comes in this is known
as sulet
uh this API got invoked it will do some
processing and return the response so
this actually which handles the request
processes it and Returns the uh send the
response back is known as
sulet and what is sulet container a
sulet containers are the one which
manages the
suets so there can be so many
suets so sulet containers are the which
manage this suets which manage this
suets okay so I will come to this
diagram but let me first tell you in a
very easy manner how we used to write a
web application very simple only one uh
you can say that one class I will tell
you so this is how suet used to look
like okay so I have defined my uh AP API
here so here at the web sulet SL demo
sulet right one demo sulet one so this
is you can say that my API and I extend
it with HTTP sulet so a one sulet can
have only one do get do put do Post do
delete right uh these are the in uh
methods which we have to override and
Pro the
implementation
so here if you see that this is the
sulet and in this method any get request
which comes it will comes to this so it
will get comes to this I am doing
processing and ultimately will send the
response if required So currently I void
no response so any response will go so
HTTP response will go in the this
response I can set it
here okay so this is known as suet
so this is I make another subet because
we can have more than one suets so
that's why I created another subet and
give them the name demo sulet
2 okay so in this sulet also I can have
do get do put do Post do delete right
and do something and return if
required so I can have multiple
cets so there is something called
web.xml and this is the culprate
actually which makes everything too
complex so what in the web.xml there are
so many things we used to do filtering
and all right but let's keep aside uh
the one thing which we have to do is the
sulet
mapping so what sulet mapping is that so
this is one sulet demo sulet one right
so this is the sulet name demo sulet one
what all URL this will handle
okay what all URL this will handle so
let's say slash demo sulet 1 this if if
customer hit this URL let's say demo
sulet 1 okay so it will comes to this
subet so this subet will handle so
that's what its mapping is if user
invoke this API SL demo sulet one slash
first endpoint some endpoint which subet
will handle there are multiple subet
subet one subet 2 subet 3 subet 100 so
if customer hit this API which sulet
will handle so I have mapped it to sulet
one this sulet so that API will come to
here this sulet one and after this it
will go inside a particular method if
user has hit the get HTTP request get so
it will go inside do get and check the
request info okay first endpoint SL demo
sulet
1 and user hit first end point so okay
this LF will get
executed okay and if user hit this API
if user hit this API so in the sulet
mapping web.xml it has been mapped to
which sulet suet demo sublet one so it
will goes to the demo sublet one and
let's say it is again a get call so it
will goes to the do get and then it will
check all the if condition okay
uh this is the this LS if condition got
matched SLC and point so this this
processing will start so you got it if
if the put API got invoke put slash demo
demo sulet 1
so what would get invoke okay demo subet
1 is the API which is mapped
to this AP this sulet okay this sulet
will invoke this is the put so it will
goes to dop put and then it will see
okay this is the path and do the
processing so similarly another mapping
I have done is for my second sulet so
this is how sulet used to work now let's
come to to this
diagram so when input request comes
in it first has to goes to the Tomcat
this is the server which is also known
as actually
your seret container right this is not
service container uh my bad it's serlet
container so Tomcat used to know uh also
known as serlet
container okay so we have to deploy our
application here in the Tom sulet
container so our application has all
this sulet subet 2 and all this we will
convert it to war and we will deploy it
here in the
tomit now what this suet container will
do I told you that subet containers are
the one which manages the sulet so what
it will do is at the first it will
invoke use the web.xml and see that hey
user has
invoked
demo
CET
1/ first end
point who so now this sulet container
will use this web.xml this mappings and
identify which subet has to be invoked
so in web.xml it will check that okay uh
demo subet one first endpoint yeah demo
sulet one uh first endpoint this one
which sulet going to be handled this is
the name sulet name demo sulet 1 okay so
this is the name demo sulet one which
class demo sulet so I have kept the name
and class name same so this is the name
you can give any name so with this name
it will find out the mapping class so
this class will get invoked and this
class is the sulet class so it now know
which sulet has to invoke and then
ultimately it call the sulet right so it
will call this demo sulet one
right that particular method because it
knows that it's a get call right so it
will invoke its do get method and now
this sulet would should be able to
handle it okay so this piece of code
would be executing it and it will send
the response
back so you got the how subet used to
work now there are certain problems in
it which
spring frame
framework
solves right spring Frameworks is you
can say that is a family which has lot
of
features right and you can say that even
spring
boot is comes under this spring
framework only okay but I would say that
before spring boot comes there is
something called that spring MVC this
comes before even spring boot okay so we
will come to Spring boot
so to solve the
issues of the sulet I will tell you the
issues spring MVC comes into the picture
so what all problems it solves so spring
framework solves challenges which exist
with
suets what
first removal of web.xml
this web.xml becomes too big so because
see when you work on a production level
application where it takes handles uh
millions and billions of
requests this one subet two subet there
can be hundred of suets and to have the
mappings of those hundreds of
subet it become too big right also this
web.xml holds lot of information like
filtering any request comes it has to go
through filter what sequence of
filtering it has to go that also
maintains over here so this web.xml is
contains lot of
information and it become very difficult
to manage and understand
it so spring framework introduce
annotation based configuration so
removal of web.xml completely makes
developer life lot easy because now
developer can work through
annotations okay okay so the the second
advantage of a spring framework
is inversion of control very important
ioc so what ioc definition is ioc is
more flexible way to manage object
dependencies and its life cycle through
dependency
injection so sometimes you say that hey
dependency injection and sometimes some
people say ioc both are same so
generally you can say dependency
injection is an implementation of ioc
okay so sometimes somebody calls ioc
sometimes somebody say dependency
injection but they both are same okay so
what is uh inversion of control uh I'll
I I'll tell you here let's see this
example then we'll come back to more
advantages okay so here if you see that
consider this example simple Java class
okay in this simple Java class I have
created a payment class and I this
payment cloud is depend on this user so
I am creating an object of this
user there is a simple method get Sender
details ID so what I'm doing is I'm
using this object
sender calling its method get user
detail and passing the
ID so what it will do is it will invoke
this user class this
method pass the ID and it will fetch
certain data of this ID and maybe return
it or do something okay so what is the
problem you see I see there is one major
problem is very tight coupling so there
is a very tight coupling between payment
and user class you can ask me right hey
sh what do you mean by tight coupling
here so see this
is I can tell you what like what I mean
by tight coupling suppose I want to
write unit test cases for the payment
get Sender details method you already
know that unit test cases
means only if let's say if I'm writing a
unit test cases for this payment class
right so I should have the capability to
test this method only this method if
this method is
invoking some outside different class
method I should be able to mock it mock
it in the sense okay send. dot if
whenever this is in called let's say I
should always get this value so I mock
this that's what unit testing is
right you should be able to mock the
data which you are not
testing okay so as in the mock testing
of this class and this method I should
not test this so that's why I should be
able to mock it but will you be able to
mock if you are creating a new object
here if you are creating a new object
here it will definitely call this for
sure so how you will mock it there is no
way right so definitely writing a unit
test cases would going to be very very
difficult so how the inversion of
control or dependency injections solve
it so ining
framework again was don't worry about
this
annotations I will explain The
annotation in the upcoming session but
this uh component autowired what is the
usage of this
component just keep aside first but just
understand the concept right so with the
dependency injection what problem we
solve is so now here
we have used certain annotation which
tells the spring that hey you manage it
okay so here if you see that user I have
given atate component and now this I
handle it to
the uh spring hey you manage this Bean
okay you manage this class similarly
payment also I have created at theate
component and this class is also now get
managed by
spring and here I have put at theate
Auto so Auto tells the spring to resolve
and add this object dependency whenever
this class get
initiated okay so now whenever this
class get initiated what spring will say
that okay at theate Auto is there means
I need to create an object of it okay so
it will resolve it spring will resolve
the dependency it will create
object we are not creating object here
like
this okay so what advantage we get here
the advantage is let's say that first
unit test
cases unit test cases I can mock it I
can tell a
spring H create a mock data for it mock
it now during run time a spring will
create a
mock object of it and using that mock
object I can say that Hey whenever that
Mo mock user object do get something has
been
invoked do do this okay so what happened
is that now we have the
control okay so here I haven't hardcoded
it like new user which always create a
new user
I now this is getting managed by Spring
and this process is known as dependency
injection unit testing is much harder in
sulet and I I already told you how it
become easy in the spring through
dependency injection we have already
seen the
process difficult to manage rest API as
you already see
that each sulet can have only one get
method one put method one post method
right one particular
solet but let's say there can be for
this subet let's say there could be 10
apis which has to handle so generally
this is how it should it we used to do
if else if else if okay so in this path
which is handled by this
of whenever this path comes do this
whenever this path comes for the get do
this whenever for get this path come do
this so it's not very you can say that
uh flexible way to handle the uh input
request which is coming right so path
mapping makes code little difficult to
understand that's what I used to feel
right so spring mvy provide an organized
approach to handle the request and it's
easy to build restful API I'll tell you
like
very very simple we are also using it
right uh very easy way so here if you
see I have also taken an example this
one so we we have like at theate get
mapping this path now you can have
another at theate another get
mapping let's say at theate
payment some certain my endpoint certain
endpoint let's say
one right so you you uh and it's method
public
string public string some let's say
method now do something so in one class
we don't have to have like all the get
apis if else if else if else you can
have proper if there are 10 get apis you
can have 10 mappings properly so it's
very easy to understand it's uh you can
say that more organized way of handling
the request
okay so it's easy to build restful
apis so there are many more advantages
of a spring framework and the spring
framework brings lot of other Advantage
I have already told you that integration
lot of Integrations are present okay
developer can choose different
combination of Technologies and
framework which best fits their
requirement for example for unit testing
you can choose junit mockito integration
is available in Spring you can start
using it
let's say for data you can use uh
hibernate jdbc jpa lot of integration
available if you want hibernate based
upon your specific need go ahead use it
if you want jdbc go ahead use it
similarly for asynchronous programming
caching messaging security all
Integrations present this will take your
picture Cod clear your picture
completely okay about this spring
framework so request comes in
again like a same here we have something
called subet
container so tomit is the subet
container we have to deploy our
application here remember the word I'm
saying we have to
deploy right so whatever the application
we have we have to create a
war deploy it here in the subet
container Tomkin okay why I am focusing
it more because it will it's an
advantage of a spring boot I'll come to
that
so in the spring framework or you can
say that in the spring MVC earlier when
request comes in it goes to the subet
container in the subet container which
is uh Tomcat we have deployed our
application then it the request goes to
dispatcher subet it is also known as the
first
controller also known as first
controller dispatcher
sulet okay
so in the spring these
classes uh where yeah these classes
right where we have exposed the apis
right this is known as
controller right so we can have so many
controller classes
right let's say I have this uh payment
controller right I have this payment
controller class I have put The
annotation controller to tell the spring
that this is the controller class so any
API will come you will find certain
mapping here so similarly I can have so
many controller class let's say that
class order order controller I will also
have annotation at theate controller
here sales controller something so so
many controller class there so which
controller class to invoke for this API
so let's say that the request come is
slash uh demo
slash
.1 this API comes now which controller
will handle it in the subet this is
going to do that stuff subet container
but in Spring
no spring there is something called
dispatcher ofet so this subet container
pass it to dispatcher subet all the end
points now this dispatcher ofet which is
also known as first controller will
decide which ultimately controller I
have to pass this require and how it
will do so first it will choose the
controller and it uses Handler mapping
okay so here we are doing request
mapping here if you see these are the
anot
I told you we are not doing web.xml we
are not creating web.xml
in Spring framework annotations we are
using it so you can just see that
internally it might be doing certain XML
configuration and all but for us it's a
simple annotation that we have mapped
this class we have mapped this payment
controller
class to handle this request mapping at
the rate payment
API okay so like this mapping we have
done so first dispatcher sub dispatcher
subet uses the Handler mapping to know
which controller to
invoke now it knows that okay uh for
example payment API now let's say
instead of this demo it is/ payment
API now based on this uh Handler mapping
it knows that okay okay it has to invoke
this controller payment
controller okay now it has to create an
instance right
because I have uh because here in the
spring we cannot you won't find anywhere
uh equals to new equals to new
so dispatcher ofet is now going to
create an instance of what create an
instance of your controller class
payment controller so now now it will
create an instance of your payment
controller
and it will use it will use or you can
say that the leverage ioc inversion of
control
now now what it will do is that okay I
need to create an instance of payment
controller but for for that I have to
also resolve the dependencies if there
are any so it will see that okay ioc now
it will goes to the ioc ioc uses
dependency uh injection and with that it
will say that okay at the rate auto
means this payment controller is
dependent on
this object I have to resolve it so now
ioc will create an object for this and
inject it right so it will on the fly it
will now create an object of it and
populated with the
object okay so now the instance is
created for this
and all the dependencies are resolved
for this which are where this class
depend on is all the auto wires are
resolved by whom by
ioc right all the dependencies are
injected now what it will do is it will
dispatcher will invoke the controller
method particular method so now that
particular method let's say the API was
uh end point is let's say
slash payment API slash payment this is
the request so it will say that okay SL
payment it will invoke this particular
get
mapping okay so here if you see that
these
mappings helping the dispatcher subad to
determine which controller and which
method to invoke which controller and
which method to
invol
okay so is it clear like when I'm saying
Handler mapping what does what does it
mean this mappings request mapping get
mapping these are ultimately helping the
dispatcher ofet to determine which
controller to call and in this
controller which method to invo based
upon this API which is coming it will do
this
mappings and find out the controller and
Method so ultimately in unvoke the
controller method so this will now
process it and then ultimately return it
and it
goes so spring framework is clear right
where the ioc comes into the picture
actually
right okay so till now you clear that
from the journey from
sulet to
Spring framework which is spring MVC see
you know the advantage now why what's
the need of a spring boot now what's the
use of spring
boot but before uh spring boot uh let's
see the one example of uh spring mvca so
that will clarify when we will see the
advantage of a spring boot so this is a
very very simple spring MVC application
you can say that okay I have created a
controller class One controller class
like P
controller put again ignore the
annotations we will see The annotation
in depth but for now just remember this
is one of the controller one one of the
controller class
where kind of a similar to sulet where
any request comes in processes it and
return it okay and these are the mapping
in sulet we were doing a mapping in
web.xml in Spring MVC these are the
annotations we are using and it mapping
whenever any API comes in so these
mappings helps which controller should
handle it and what method and dispatcher
ofet is going to use
it so this class is created this is
something called pom.xml where we have
written the dependencies so this is
first dependency let's say we are
creating a web application web uh spring
uh MVC so we have created its
version then you want subet you have
created its version added dependency
let's say if you want unit test cases
junit you have added its dependency with
the version so for simpler perceptive I
have written three
dependencies uh you can write into the
pom.xml this is May one right so I have
written three
dependencies the another class is app
config so this CL in this uh class
generally in the spring mcy see we have
this annotation important where what
this tells is that it loads lot of
dependencies which spring Embassy is
required right so it loads all of
it then another annotation you atate
component scan so we provide a package
so what is this only within this
package you are telling that hey Spring
only within within this package and
Below you go and
manage whatever the controllers or
whatever the controllers I am creating
it right uh controllers beans and all so
we are
telling spring to do a scanning whatever
because uh spring has to search right
the controller and everything so we have
to give it a path from where it has to
start searching for the component
scanning so we can provide it here
so that's where it's known as
configuration classes uh because it load
configuration for spring embassies which
is required to work and also component
can we Define it
here and I told you that dispatcher
sulet is used in Spring
MVC and this dispatcher sulet is the
first
controller all the request from subet
controller comes to it and it it perform
all the stuffs select choose the
controller create an instance so that's
why there is one called dispatcher sulet
class we have to create like this in
Spring MVC we have to extend this uh
dispatcher ofet this one and we have to
provide this three methods we have to
override this three
methods provide what is the config class
we can provided that this is our config
because this class name can be anything
right so we have to give like what is is
the config class so any dependency it
required it can uh load it enable MVC
right this is an annotation uh so this
annotation load lot of spring MVC kind
of libraries
internally then subet mapping so we have
told that any request coming with this
slash itself you have to handle it right
so those also we have mentioned in this
dispatcher subet what all request we it
has to handle so this means
all okay so this if you see that even a
basic application I am writing I have to
have one controller this form this
config and this dispatcher subet and you
already know what is the dispatcher
sulet does controller and ioc and
all so this spring framework is clear
now you can tell me hey sh why is spring
boot is
required what problem is spring boot
solve why it exists today spring boot
Sol challenges which exist with spring
MVC three big things
first dependency
management here if you see that in the
spring for.xml spring
MVC is spring
MVC if you focus a little bit you are
adding a
dependency whatever you
required and you also have to provide
the
version you also have to provide the
version now let's say that in future you
have to upgrade the version of J units
from let's say
4.3.2 to let's say 5.1.2
something but will this version work
with this version
also it it might it might not because
you know that the dependencies should be
compatible with each
other so this is one problem with the
spring dependency
management so no need for adding
different dependencies separately and
also their compatible version heading
Springs keep it
easy so spring boot keep it easy you
have to just give like
this starter web and starter test
so this web already internally it will
load whatever dependency it require to
create a web application this will load
whatever the dependency it required for
testing so it will automatically add the
dependency for you and here also if you
see you don't you are not defining any
versions
also so you don't have to worry it will
automatically uh load those version
which are compatible with each other and
internally it will load all the
dependencies which might required for
creating a web application here you
might require 1520 dependencies I have
written only three but it might require
1520 but here you might only need two
internally it will
load all in here you need is that this
parent that's all what spring boot
version you are using three version
that's all you only you have to define
the spring version here starter parent
version rest all this thing you don't
have to define the version itself
internally it will keep loading keep
adding the version it is now spring boot
had so dependency management is the
first advantage of a spring boot over
spring
MVC okay so understand this that this is
your
spring
MVC this is your spring
boot so all the benefits of spring MVC
is also present into spring boot plus
additional something so dependency
management is same thing it is doing the
same thing spring boot is doing the same
thing as spring MVC but now it's a
little bit abstracted to
us second thing is second Advantage is
auto configuration here if you see that
this dispatcher solet this is kind of a
configuration right this class is kind
of a configuration this class is also a
configuration web mnc's app config right
these are lot of configuration class so
that's why the another advantage of
spring board is auto
configuration no need for separately
configuring dispatcher ofet app config
you don't need to Define component SCAN
Web uh enable web MVC is spring boot
internally add by default values for
it so spring boot internally will add by
default values of at theate component
scan so wherever your application uh
start applic ation exist main method
from that package onwards it will start
so what it does
is uh there was a term called if I
remember correctly there was a term
called op op opinion
opiniated just double check once I think
that's why we call that spring boot has
opiniated nature means it will give
opinion so it opinion means it choose by
default hey component scan I am choosing
the package as from wherever your
application main method starts that
package I will choose so if most of the
time you can go ahead with this spring
board
opinion okay so that's why you don't
have to write this but let's say that if
you are not agree with spring boot
opinion or by default you can anyway add
this your own also I will tell you you
can add it
but that's why it is known as Auto
configuration
means no need for separately configur
configuring all this dispatcher solet
app config component discan spring boot
add internally by default but if you
want you can in this springboard class
you can add component scan if you want
to change the default
values right we will see that uh at
theate component scan what does it mean
and all don't worry about this but
understand what is mean by Auto
configuration and there is a term called
I think opiated that's the same thing
spring boot gives the opinion that I am
using this so if you are agree with this
opinion you don't need this
configuration or it's autoconfigure if
you deviate from its opinion you have
you can write component scan and give
your package from where to
start so only one class you required
here in Spring boot is this spring boot
this annotation spring boot application
annotation so this annotation itself
internally has at theate enable web
MVC atate component scan dispatcher
sulet all the configuration Auto
configuration are you can say that
hidden inside this one annotation
itself and this is uh your main method
the start of the
application okay so second ADV Vantage
is clear Auto configuration there is now
you don't need to create this class you
don't need to create this class you
don't need to do at theate component
scan everything is taken care by Spring
boot itself so now it's very clean class
one and the third very big Advantage is
embedded server so from if you remember
I was focusing on the term that we have
to deploy or we have to first create a v
of our application
and deploy that into the Tomcat which is
a sulet
container okay in both sulet and spring
MVC but in Spring
boot in Spring boot server is already
embeded you don't have to generate a VAR
you don't have to take a VAR and deploy
it to a tom cat or subet
container server is already embedded
inside it it automat atically does it
for us we don't have to do
it right seret container is already
embedded we don't have to do all this
stuff just run the application I will
tell you
how so what is a spring boot in simple
term it provide a quick way to create a
production ready
application it is based on Spring config
spring framework only spring MVC it
support convention over configuration I
already told told you that auto
configuration part right it uses default
values for configuration and if
developer don't want to go with
convention they the way something is
done they can override it convention
means the way something is done default
values if you don't agree with the
default values you can always override
it that is convention over configuration
means so it support convention over
configuration it also helps to run an
application as quick as
possible
right so
now this is very simple here if you see
that form. XML is very simple here
parent. parent is there where with the
version but now it's dependency here if
you see that only two dependency you
don't have to add more you don't have to
add version also so you don't have to
worry about dependency management there
is nothing no configuration you created
One controller
class I have defined controller class
I have defined the mapping which API uh
one get call for
sample and this is the start application
I told you why it is required all the
auto configuration here hidden inside it
now now when you start this application
this
method and if you on the Chrome if you
just call this if the client is invoking
this slash my
API SL first API spring boot is nothing
but a spring MVC right the same
dispatcher subet is hidden to us but
internally dispatcher sofl will use this
mapping it will identify okay my API
which
controller okay my API is mapped to this
my controller okay first API which
method this get method will get invoke
and it will print this hello from
concept and coding so dispatcher subet
will create an object of it
and it will pass it to ioc if there is
any depend to resolve any dependency if
there at the rate autowire nothing is
there so no need of ioc it just simply
create an object of this and invoke
this okay so let me show you here this
is the spring boot here if you see I am
just simply
running run here if you see that Tom cat
is started so I don't have to create War
I don't don't have to deploy
automatically server started on this
port now we can just simply go and in
the Chrome we can add this API Local
Host uh this is on this is the port
where it is
started and this is the API I am hitting
so this is the API I have
return controller my
API and this is the endpoint first API
if I press enter hello from concept and
coding hello from concept and coding
don't worry about this setup of this
project that we will see in the uh
second part uh second session but focus
on the points like advant why spring
boot needed at the first place that was
the big I can tell you just three
advantage of this embedded server Auto
configuration dependency management and
I can simply cover this whole video in
15 20 minutes itself but with without
understanding the
suets what problem exists what spring
MVC solves it and what are the problem
in Spring MVC itself which spring board
solvers without that it's a partial
knowledge but I hope you uh like it and
you will share it with uh your
connection if you think it will help
them so thank you for that and see you
in next video bye